A Finding Aid to the Ilse Getz Papers, 1928-1999, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ilse Getz papers
1928-1999
Archives of American Art
Getz, Ilse, 1917-
AAA.getzilse
Archival Resource Key
3.4 Linear feet
The papers of collage artist Ilse Getz measure 3.4 linear feet and date from 1928 through 1999, with the bulk of the papers dating from circa 1947-circa 1990. Her personal life is reflected through biographical material including a genealogy of the Bechhold family; marriage and death certificates; and writings that include journals, artist statement, poems and notes. The collection contains letters from friends, artists, collectors, and museum and art gallery representatives; exhibition files; and printed material relating to Getz's exhibitions. Also found are photographs, slides and transparencies of artwork.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 6 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1934-1996 (Box 1, OV 5; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Letters, circa 1950-1999 (Box 1; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, circa 1944-1990 (Box 1, 2, 4; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1928-1987 (Box 2, 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1956-1990 (Box 2, 3, 4, OV 5; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1940-1985 (Box 3; 0.5 linear feet)
Biographical / Historical
Ilse Getz (1917-1992) was born in Nuremberg, Germany and immigrated to the U.S. in 1933. She studied at the Art Students League with George Grosz and Morris Kantor and at the Ozenfant School. Getz was a collage and construction artist active from the 1950s through the 1980. She exhibited at several galleries in New York City including the Bertha Schaefer Gallery and Rosenberg Gallery.
During her childhood, Ilse Getz (nee Bechhold) had been uprooted both from home and country. She was first displaced in 1929, when she was sent to Hamburg to live with her sister after her father died by suicide. In 1933, Ilse and her sister left Nazi Germany, and traveled to Italy, Spain, Cuba, and Mexico. Ilse joined immediate family in New York. In 1937, Ilse married lawyer David Getz and settled in Allentown, Pennsylvania. Three years later she had a child and became a naturalized citizen of the United States.
In 1942, while visiting her sister in Mexico, Getz created her first oil painting. Upon returning to New York, Ilse continued her artistic exploration and studied with George Grosz and Morris Kantor at the Art Students League. By 1945, Getz had already held her first solo exhibition at the Norlyst Gallery in New York.
Getz traveled extensively throughout her life, incorporating the experiences in her work. During 1947-1948, she traveled and worked in Europe, visiting Switzerland, France, Spain and Portugal among other countries before retiring for four months in Guaruja, Brazil. She destroyed most of the artwork created during that period and returned to New York City.
During the summer of 1956, Getz taught and exhibited at the Positano Art Workshop in Italy along with Piero Dorazio. She repeated the experience two years later. In 1958, Getz married her second husband, artist Manoucher Yektai. The following year, Getz and Yektai went to Yaddo in Saratoga Springs, New York after having received fellowships to the artists' community.
In 1960, Getz was commissioned by Richard Barr to create the set for Eugene Ionesco's play, The Killer. The venue was the Seven Arts Theater in New York City and she completed the set in five days. Getz spent the next two years in Paris where she was represented by the Iris Clert Gallery; she exhibited in France, Germany and England. In 1962, Getz returned to New York City and maintained a studio on the Upper East Side. Getz married for the third time in 1964 to Gibson Danes who was then the Dean of Yale School of Art and Architecture. The couple lived in New York and Connecticut, and eventually settled in Newtown, Connecticut.
Getz participated in national and international exhibitions and in solo and group shows. Her collages and constructions incorporate items such as dolls, toys, birds, eggs, playing cards, and game boards. In 1978, retrospective exhibitions of Getz's work were held at the Neuberger Museum in Purchase, New York and in her native city at the Kunsthalle Nürnberg. Retrospective exhibitions were also held in 1980 at the Goethe House and Alex Rosenberg Gallery.
Later in life, Getz suffered from advanced Alzheimer's disease. In 1992, Gibson Danes, fearful that he would no longer be able to properly care for his wife, took both his life and that of Ilse Getz. They were found dead in their garage from acute carbon monoxide toxicity after breathing the fumes of their idling car.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated in 2001 by Patricia Getz-Gentle, the daughter of Ilse Getz.
Scope and Contents
The papers of collage artist Ilse Getz measure 3.4 linear feet and date from 1928 through 1999, with the bulk of the papers dating from circa 1947-circa 1990. Her personal life is reflected through biographical material including a genealogy of the Bechhold family; marriage and death certificates; and writings that include journals, artist statement, poems and notes. The collection contains letters from friends, artists, collectors, and museum and art gallery representatives; exhibition files; and printed material relating to Getz's exhibitions. Also found are photographs, slides and transparencies of artwork.
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Diaries; Photographs; Women artists; Women painters; Collagists -- New York (State) -- New York
- Biographical Material, circa 1934-1996; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, OV 5
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes curriculum vitae, chronology of Ilse Getz's life, list of collectors, certificate of naturalization and passport, obituaries and death records for Ilse Getz and her husband Gibson Danes, memorial service program and certificate of devise, and a genealogy of the Bechhold family. This series also houses a scrapbook of clippings and exhibition announcements that document Getz's early artistic career. Researchers should note that some of the information in the scrapbook can also be found elsewhere in the collection, primarily in sereies 3 and 5 and additional material can be and additional material is found in series 4.
  - Curriculum Vitae, Chronologies, and List of Collectors, 1974; 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Naturalization and Passport, 1940; 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Obituaries and Death Records, Ilse Getz and Gibson Danes, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memorial Service Program, Certificate of Devise, and Condolence Letters, 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bechhold Family Genealogy (includes Photocopies), circa 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clipping, Marriage Announcement, 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1944-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Research Foundation for Jewish Immigration, Inc., 1981-1982; circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Supplemental Issue and Application Form for Who's Who publication, circa 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Oversized, Research Foundation for Jewish Immigration, Inc. from box 1, folder 8, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
- Letters, circa 1950-1999; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains personal and professional letters written to Ilse Getz from friends, artists, museum and gallery representatives, and collectors. Personal letters from artists and gallery representatives are from Kenneth Armitage, Varujan Boghosian, Ludwig Charell, Virginia and Piero Dorazio, Theodoros Stamos, Mark Tobey, and Manoucher Yektai, among others. Professional letters from artists and museum and gallery representatives are included from Carol Anthony, Roy Davis, Louise Tolliver Deutschman, S. Lane Faison, Sigrid Freundorfer, Curt Heigl, Paul Jenkins, Jirko Jirí Chmelar, Hans Namuth, Pierre Restany, and Judith Rothschild among others. Also included are season's greeting cards from Sonia Delauney and Larry Aldrich. This series also houses letters pertaining to the 1978 retrospective exhibition Ilse Getz - Bilder, Konstruktionen, Collagen, which took place at the Kunsthalle Nürnberg in Germany. There are a few draft response letters written by Ilse Getz. Where dates are unknown, letters have been filed at the end of a folder.
  - Letters to Ilse Getz, 1950-1951; 1953-1959; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Ilse Getz, 1961-1967; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Ilse Getz, 1962; 1971-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Ilse Getz, 1976-1979; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Ilse Getz, 1980-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters to Ilse Getz, 1985-1989; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Allentown Art Museum and Phillip Hack, circa 1974-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Carol Anthony, circa 1986-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sigrid Freundorfer, circa 1977-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Kunsthalle Nürnberg, circa 1976-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Joel Mallin, Collector (includes Financial Records), circa 1978-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Monograph, Collaging with Paper, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Exhibition Files, circa 1944-1990; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1, 2, 4
  Exhibition files may contain any or all of the following: sales and loan records; letters; photographs; publicity material; and price lists. Included in the printed material are announcements, catalogs, and clippings. Financial and publicity material relating to exhibitions are located at the beginning of the series. Individual files on exhibitions are listed chronologically. Some files may contain multiple exhibition information. Additional material can be found in series 2.
  - Artwork Sales and Loan Records, circa 1958-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Publicity Material, 1944-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Price Lists, Various Exhibitions, 1959-1963; circa 1977-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Third Annual Invitation Exhibition by Regional Artists, Guild Hall, East Hampton, New York, 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Multiple Exhibitions, Bertha Schaefer Gallery, New York, New York, circa 1954-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Paintings and Collages by Ilse Getz and Ilse Getz Paintings, Gump's Gallery, San Francisco, California, 1957-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Ilse Getz: Collage Paintings (1960), Widdifield Gallery, New York, New York, 1959-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Battered City Donated Getz Artwork, Dartmouth College Hopkins Center, Hanover, New Hampshire, circa 1960-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Multiple Exhibitions, Iris Clert Gallery, Paris, France, circa 1961-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Collage Paintings and Boxes (1966), and Ilse Getz, Constructions, Collages and Paintings (1978), Elaine Benson Gallery, Bridgehampton, New York, circa 1977-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Ilse Getz Dartmouth College Hopkins Center Art Galleries, Hanover, New Hampshire, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Multiple Exhibitions, Gimpel Weitzenhoffer Ltd., New York, New York, circa 1972-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Paintings and Constructions Williams College Museum of Art, Williamstown, Massachusetts, and Allentown Art Museum, Allentown, Pennsylvania, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Ilse Getz: Oils, Constructions (1975), Galerie Kostiner-Silvers, Inc., Montreal, Canada, circa 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Multiple Exhibitions, The Aldrich Museum of Contemporary Art, Ridgefield, Connecticut, 1974-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Permanent Collection, Joseph and Olga Hirshhorn and Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden, Washington, D.C., circa 1975-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ilse Getz: Retrospective 1957-1977 (1978), Neuberger Museum, Purchase, New York, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ilse Getz Recent Works: Boxes, Constructions and Collages (1980), Alex Rosenberg Gallery, New York, New York, circa 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Multiple Exhibitions, Stamford Museum & Nature Center, Stamford, Connecticut, 1978; 1984-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Collages and Constructions (1978), and Face Off (1988), Washington Art Association, Washington Depot, Connecticut, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ilse Getz Retrospective: Boxes, Constructions, and Collages (1980), Goethe House, New York, New York, 1980-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Three Friends (1984), and The Woman from Nostalgia to Neuralgia (1985), Paris-New York-Kent Gallery, Kent, Connecticut, circa 1980-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Multiple Exhibitions, Silvermine Guild Center for the Arts, New Canaan, Connecticut, circa 1981-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ilse Getz: Key West Winters, Newtown Summers (1982), Alex Rosenberg Gallery, New York, New York, circa 1982-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Various Charity Exhibitions, circa 1983-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ilse Getz: Selections from the 70s and 80s Almquist Gallery, New Preston, Connecticut, circa 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Women Artists of Connecticut (1987), The Connecticut Gallery, Marlborough, Connecticut, circa 1986-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Constructions Mattatuck Museum, Waterbury, Connecticut, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - All About Woman Paris-New York-Kent Gallery, Kent, Connecticut, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - East Hampton Avant-Garde: A Salute to the Signa Gallery Guild Hall Museum, East Hampton, New York, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Various Exhibitions, circa 1944-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-20)
  - Artwork Sales and Loan Records from box 1, folder 22-23, Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Paintings and Constructions Williams College Museum of Art, Williamstown, Massachusetts, and Allentown Art Museum, Allentown, Pennsylvania from box 1, folder 36, Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Writings, circa 1928-1987; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2, 4
  Writings contain an artist statement, notes, journals, poems by Getz and Barbara Guest, and a transcribed interview from 1977 of Ilse Getz conducted by Carl Heigl. Also found is an illustrated travel journal created in 1947 in which Getz recorded her experiences while visiting Spain. Included in the material is a journal from Getz's youth in which friends and acquaintances wrote notes and drawings to her. Writings by others include a statement by Paul Jenkins titled, "Thoughts around Ilse." This series is arranged according to material type and chronologically.
  - Artist's Statement, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Artists, Critics, and Students on Ilse Getz, circa 1966-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Journal, Drawing and Notes to Ilse Bechhold from Friends and Acquaintances, 1928-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Journal, Recollections of Travels in Spain (includes Artwork), 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Journal (includes Poems and Sketches), circa 1953-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Notes, Biographical, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Notes, Travel, circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Notes, Various Galleries and Miscellaneous, circa 1984-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Poems, circa 1952-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Poem, Barbara Guest, circa 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Transcribed Interview with Ilse Getz conducted by Carl Heigl, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Poem, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Printed Material, circa 1956-1990; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 2, 3, 4, OV 5
  Printed material contains announcements, invitations, solo and group exhibition catalogs, and clippings pertaining to Getz's artistic career. Also included are posters for exhibitions in which Getz participated with a monograph of the Artist's Christmas Cards which features a reproduction of Getz's work.
  Included within the material are an acquisitions report from Dartmouth College Museums & Galleries and an annual report from the Wadsworth Atheneum, which list the gift of Getz's work to the institutions. Also found are group exhibition catalogs including Collage International: From Picasso to the Present, Contemporary Arts Museum, 1958; Cinquante Ans de "Collages" Musée d'Art et d'Industrie, 1964; and Grandes Femmes Petits Formats, Micro-Salon 1974, inscribed by Iris Clert-Christofle. Solo exhibition catalogs include Ilse Getz, Collage Paintings, Tibor Nagy Gallery, 1962; Ilse Getz, Paintings, Collages, Constructions Neuberger Museum, and Kunsthalle Nürnberg, 1978; and Ilse Getz, Boxes, Collages, & Constructions Alex Rosenberg Gallery and Goethe House, 1978, among others. Magazine and newspaper clippings include reviews of Getz's work by Larry Campbell, Henry Lehmann. Virginia Mann, Vivien Raynor, and Sidney Tillim.
  - Institutional Reports, Annual and Acquisitions, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1945-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33-36)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Group Exhibitions, circa 1947-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Solo Exhibitions, 1962-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Gallery Guide Clippings, 1965; 1978-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Magazine Clippings, 1957-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11-14)
    Oversized material housed in box 4, folder 5
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15-18)
    Oversized material can be found in box 4, folders 6-8
  - Transcribed Clippings, circa 1944-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Magazines, 1961; 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Monograph, Artist's Christmas Cards, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Newsletter, Yaddo, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Exhibition Posters, 1957-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Oversized material housed in OV 5
  - Magazine Clippings from box 3, folders 11-14, Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings from box 3, folders 15-18, Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Kunsthalle Nürnberg, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Monthly and Bi-Monthly Newspapers, 1978-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Oversized, Newspaper Clippings, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
  - Oversized, Exhibition Posters from box 4, folder 4, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
- Photographs, circa 1940-1985; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 3
  This series contains photographs, slides and transparencies of Ilse Getz's artwork. Images of artwork primarily consist of Polariods. Also included are slides and negatives of Ilse Getz in her Newtown, Connecticut studio as well as a photograph of her New York City studio and apartment. Also included is a photograph of Getz's friend and fellow artist, Theodoros Stamos.
  - Negatives of Artwork, circa 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Photograph of Theodoros Stamos and Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Photograph of Studio and Apartment in New York City, circa 1940-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Photographs and Slides of Artwork, circa 1944-1950; circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Photographs (including Polaroids) and Slides of Artwork in Collections, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Polaroids of Artwork in Collections, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29-31)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Slides and Negatives of Ilse Getz and Studio, circa 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Transparencies of Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 34-35)